in this video I look at some overall
stats on the potential benefits and
risks of eating a plant-based diet it's
a great introductory video if you're
just getting started or want to share
with friends and family check it out
[Music]
vegetarian diets and Lifestyles have
been shown to reduce the risk of many
chronic diseases which now accounts for
the major Global burden of disease but
the actual direct medical costs had
never been Quantified before here's what
they found same amount spent on dental
work but compared to meat eaters that
similarly don't smoke or drink or
compared to the general population
vegetarians had significantly lower
inpatient outpatient and Total Medical
Care expenditures suggesting more
plant-based eating could be an effective
strategy to save on health care costs
here's how it broke down significantly
lower cost for chronic lifestyle
conditions such as high blood pressure
and high cholesterol this makes sense
those eating plant-based diets centered
around whole plant Foods nailed the
targets for cholesterol triglycerides
and systolic and diastolic blood
pressure 93 percent of the time 97
percent of the time 88 of the time and
95 of the time respectively
nearly a 50 drop in medical costs due to
depression too that's interesting as
well as lower costs across the board
cerebrovascular disease is another name
for stroke wasn't there that study that
showed vegetarians had higher stroke
risk true but that was before two
subsequent studies found a lower risk of
stroke with a vegetarian diet and not
just by a little
for ischemic stroke the most common
clotting type of stroke vegetarians
consistently had about 60 lower risk and
for bleeding Strokes about 65 percent
lower risk than non-vegetarians and this
despite higher homocysteine due to lower
vitamin B12 intake which is what may
have led to the higher stroke risk in
the previous study
overall if you do a systematic review of
all the major studies a comprehensive
meta-analysis found a significant
protective effect of a vegetarian diet
versus the incidence and or mortality
from ischemic heart disease and
incidents from Total cancer with a vegan
diet conferring about twice the reduced
risk cancer-wise
you can also look at it the other way
what if you decide to stop eating
vegetarian and start eating meat the
Adventist Health study looked at that
and found that compared to those who
stayed vegetarian those who started
eating meat suffered at 231 increased
risk of gaining weight
166 percent increase in the risk of
developing diabetes 152 percent
increased risk of having a stroke and
146 increased risk of being diagnosed
with heart disease and if you keep
eating meat you may cut your lifespan by
three and a half years so better not
just cut out beat but cut it out for
good but it's not all or nothing even
just cutting down may help a food
pattern that emphasizes plant-derived
Foods was found to be associated with a
reduced risk of all-cause mortality
meaning living a significantly longer
life
here are the cumulative hazards of death
across categories of pro-vegetarian
eating meaning the closer you eat
towards a completely plant-based diet
the lower your risk of death Falls
the researchers conclude that there is
now evidence that the simple advice to
increase the consumption of
plant-derived foods with reduction in
the consumption of foods from animal
sources confers a survival advantage
so there are multiple benefits even
eating in the direction of a more
plant-based diet but what about any
risks despite concerns for protein
deficiency adequate amounts of protein
which means 0.8 grams per kilogram body
weights about 50 grams a day can be
consumed in a solely plant-based diet as
seen among the other billion plus people
around the world who don't eat meat
vitamin B12 deficiency on the other hand
is a very real concern without a regular
reliable source and I have videos on how
to do that either through supplements or
fortified Foods one benefit you don't
hear much about is the role our diets
play in the emergence of pandemic
infectious diseases the subject of one
of my recent books it doesn't take much
for a virus to jump from one animal to
another but there are no examples of
plant viruses ever jumping to humans for
the same reason we don't ever come down
with a really bad case of Dutch elm
disease the largest and oldest
Association of nutrition Professionals
in the world is clear plant-based diets
are appropriate for all stages of life
cycle and may actually provide health
benefits for the prevention and
treatment of certain diseases for
example vegetarians and vegans are at
reduced risk of ischemic heart disease
type 2 diabetes high blood pressure
certain types of cancers and obesity
and to learn more they encourage people
to go check out a few good websites
as the Emeritus dean of the School of
Public Health at Loma Linda once said at
a nutrition conference attitudes towards
vegetarian diets have progressed from
ridicule and skepticism to condescending
tolerance to gradual and sometimes
grudging acceptance and finally to
acclaim
[Music]
thank you